Finding Aid for the Query Club/Fugitive Agrarian Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Query Club/Fugitive Agrarian Collection
2012
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0349
.42 linear feet
HISTORY
The Query Club had its first meeting September 26, 1885 at Dr. W.E. Ward’s residence in Nashville, Tennessee. The club was founded by Olympe Trabue, who assembled a group of her friends to explore intellectual and popular topics of the day. In the early days meetings were held each week in a small room downtown in the Vendome Theater on 7th Avenue North. The present membership of the club meet the first Tuesday of the month for dinner and a paper given on a topic chosen for the year and followed by a stated “Query” related to the topic. Among the subjects for discussion by the club have been:
The Art of Engraving and Kindred Arts (1885 –86)
British Lady Intellectuals of the 20th Century (1974-75)
Remarkable Achievements of American Women (1975-76)
Unsolved Mysteries (1957-58)
The South in Contemporary Literature (1936 –37)
Several well-established Query Club traditions include the wearing of a gold and diamond question mark pin by the chairman of the club (1891) and the sending of a box of candy by the fiance or newly wed husband of a Query Club member (1897). The Query Club year ends each June with a picnic.
The Query Club celebrated its Diamond Jubilee in 1960 with a clever series of skits illustrating each 25 year period of Query Club life. In 1985 the 100th year anniversary of the Query Club was celebrated at the historic house Fairvue, home of Ellen Wemyss, daughter of a charter member of the club.
SCOPE AND CONTENT NOTE
Introduction:
“I’m not certain, but it seems to me that there may be some connections between the Fugitives and the Query Club; and if that’s so, we ought to do something about it, before it’s too late.” ----Ann McClearan Houk
This collection is comprised of a member roster and short history and 15 audio cassettes of programs and remembrances of the Fugitives and Agrarians at Vanderbilt by Query Club members during the 1993-94 year. The 2011 Query Club Cookbook is also included in this collection.
- QUERY CLUB RECORDS
  - The Query Club 1993-94 “The Fugitives and the Agrarians“Memories Preserved” Booklet with member roster. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Query Club 1885 – 1985 ( 3 copies ) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Query Club Topics for Study 1885 – 1985 – 86 (4 copies) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- INTERVIEWS WITH QUERY CLUB MEMBERS ABOUT THE FUGITIVES AND AGRARIANS CONDUCTED BY SARAH FROST STAMPS (audio cassette tapes)
  - Cheney, Frances Neel, 6 October 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Goodpasture, Virginia, 5 October 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Morrissey, Eleanor, 11 October 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rodes, Sara, 29 September 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sutherland, Jane, 28 September 1993, 1 October 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Weaver, Blanche Henry, 1 November 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wemyss, Ellen, 4 October 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- PROGRAMS PRESENTED BY QUERY CLUB MEMBERS, 1993 –94 (audio cassette tapes)
  - 5 October 1993, Molly Howell Dohrmann. Overview and Voices from the Past a program for Public Radio Station WPLN in Nashville, January 1981; time 59:00. 2 November 1993, Sarah Frost Stamps. The Query Club Remembers the Fugitives. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 7 December 1993, Ann McClearan Houk. Interviews with Margaret Lindsley Warden, Ann Battle, Jane Sutherland, and Anne Nixon; their memories of the Fugitives and Agrarians with additional material on John Crowe Ransom. 4 January 1994, Margaret Dyer Brown. Presentation on her uncle Brock Stevenson based on family interviews and memorabilia. 1 March 1994, Louise Littleton Davis. Personal memories and encounters both personal and professional (as a reporter for The Tennessean). (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 5 April 1994, Amy Parkes Crownover. Presentation on Jesse E. Wills, based on interviews with his widow, Ellen Wills. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 3 May 1994, Sally Rodes Lee. Presentation on the ongoing influence of the Fugitives and Agrarians. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- THE FUGITIVE AND AGRARIANS AND THE QUERY CLUB (audio cassette tape)
  - Interview with Frances Neel Cheney and Brainard Cheney by Molly Howell, 1 November 1979 for Public Radio Station WPLN in Nashville; time 59:30. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Query Club Cookbook (2011) (Box 1, Folder 11)